Guide to the Erasmus Hall Records 1325–1989 (bulk circa 1775–1975) MS 201
New-York Historical Society
- "Archives of Erasmus Hall High School"
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Charter
    - Original charter of Erasmus Hall Academy, granted by the Regents of New York State and signed by Governor George Clinton, 1787 November 20 (Offsite-box RC-13)
      Original charter presented to the school by Erskine H. Lott. Framed between two pieces of glass.
      N-YHS negative no. 63406
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Description
    - Cabinet of Instruction, Literature and Amusement, vol. 1 (New York: Theodore Burling), 1829 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Cabinet of Instruction, Literature, and Amusement)
      Contains an engraving and description of Erasmus Hall Academy in Vol. I, No. 15 (Apr. 16, 1829), p. 432.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Diploma
    - Two diplomas awarded to William Henry Kouwenhoven, 1880, 1883 (Offsite-box RC-13)
      • "This Testimonial of Merit is awarded to... for punctuality, deportment, and diligent attention to study during the past twelve months at Erasmus Hall Academy. (signed) John M. Ferris, President; John L. Zabriskie, Clerk; R. C. Strong, Principal. Flatbush, June 15th, 1880."
      • "This Certificate is Awarded to... inasmuch as he has completed the full term of study presented at Erasmus Hall Academy, Flatbush, Kings County, N.Y. (signed) John M. Ferris, President of the Board of Trustees; R. C. Strong, Principal. 1883."
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Expenses
    - [Financial report and estimated expenses], 1867–1895 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • "The Trustees of School District No. 1 in the Town of Flatbush present the finan. report for the year ending Sept. 30, 1867... ."
      • "Estimated Expenses for 1869–70"
      • "Expenses for the year commencing 1 Oct. 1872"
      • "Estimate of expenses for the schools in this district for the ensuing year (1894–95)"
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Floor Plans
    - Floor plans and description of the original Academy building made by Ella Suydam., 1922 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Floor Plans)
    - Floor plans for the first and second floors of the old Academy building., 1935 February 20 (Offsite-box RC-5b, Roll Erasmus Hall Academy—Floor Plans (1935))
      Rolled, on pale green paper.
    - Correspondence... regarding the layout of the rooms in the original Erasmus Hall Academy before its extensive renovation in the early 1900s, 1940, undated (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Floor Plans)
      • Letter from Daniel M. C. Hopping, Jan. 29, 1940, who it is believed was conducting the Historic American Buildings Survey (HABS) of Erasmus Hall.
      • Letters from Louise Garvin Zabriskie and Henry M. Wells, old-time Flatbush residents.
    - Front elevation and first floor plan for the old Academy building, drawn to scale., 1975 (Offsite-box RC-5b, Roll Erasmus Hall Academy—Floor Plans (1975))
      Executed by Bruce Stoller, EHHS student.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Hardware [NOT PRESENT]
    - Original hinges and hand-made nails removed from the old Academy building during restoration, [1780s?] (Box [unknown])
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—History
    - Folder of newspaper and magazine articles relating to the history of the Academy building, undated (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—History)
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Lease
    - Original lease, 1788 April (Offsite-box RC-7)
      Original lease dated first Tuesday in April 1788, in which the Trustees of the Reformed Protestant Dutch Church of Flatbush in Kings County, leased a three-acre tract to the Trustees of Erasmus Hall for a five year term.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Library
    - [Reports], 1871–1874 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • Report of Committee on Library Apparatus, Oct. 14, 1871.
      • Report of Committee on Library Apparatus, Nov. 16, 1872.
      • Report of Committee on the Library and Philosophical Apparatus, Oct. 10, 1874.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Library—Catalogue
    - Original catalogue of books in the Erasmus Hall Library, circa 1795 (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder Original catalogue, Erasmus Hall library)
      Original catalogue of books in the Erasmus Hall Library, written, according to a pencil notation on the inside cover, by Dr. Wilson, who served as principal from 1792 until 1805. 10 leaves, marbled paper covers. The numbers assigned to the books in this catalogue correspond to the number to the immediate right of the word "Libraryn" [sic] on the bookplate in each book.
    - "Catalogue of the Library made in 1838" (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder Catalogue of Erasmus Hall library, 1838, 1842)
      This notation, in the hand of the person who compiled the 1842 catalogue (q.v.), is at the top of the first page of eight leaves, in poor condition and unbound, which comprised this catalogue.
    - "Catalogue of Erasmus Hall Library. Taken 1842" (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder 1842 catalogue, Erasmus Hall library)
      This catalogue lists the books in the Academy Library by subject classification.
    - "Continuous Catalogue of the Library of Erasmus Hall. Taken 1842" (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder Catalogue of Erasmus Hall library, 1838, 1842)
      Hardcover notebook, with listing of 2756 volumes in accession order. Apparently the entries for numbers 1 through 1729 were made by the original compiler of this catalogue in 1842. The succeeding entries, in a number of different hands, were added subsequently.
    - "Catalogue of Erasmus Hall Library, Flatbush, Long Island", 1847 (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder 1847 catalogue, Erasmus Hall library)
      This catalogue is a breakdown of the library according to subject, e.g. "Philosophy—A, Biography—B, etc." According to Ella Suydam [EHHS librarian], this catalogue was compiled by Richard Van Kleek, the principal, in 1847.
    - Single leaf, listing encyclopedias in the Library, undated (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder Catalogue of Erasmus Hall library, 1838, 1842)
      This notation in the hand of the same person who compiled the 1842 catalogue: "Old catalogue with valuations, &c. (made by Mr. Leel)."
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Library—Charge System
    - "Register of Books [Ta]ken from the Library", 1840–1859 (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder Erasmus Hall Library—Record of loans)
      Hardcover notebook listing names of borrowers with names of books borrowed. Earliest entry is 1840. Latest is 1859.
    - "Erasmus Hall. Books Issued from the Library", 1859–1879 (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder Erasmus Hall Library—Record of loans)
      This hardcover notebook lists the names of borrowers with the number of the book borrowed (as taken from the catalogue of the library). Earliest entry is 1859. Endpapers at back of book have listings for 1879.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Maintenance
    - [Report of Committee on Repairs], 1872, undated (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • Report of Committee on Repairs. n.d. 1 p.
      • Report of Committee on Repairs. Nov. 16, 1872.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Programs
    - Printed programs of "Public Exhibitions" held at the Academy, 1844–1890 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—"Public Exhibitions" (Programs))
      8 pieces and one duplicate. Accompanied by typed transcript.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Receipts
    - A receipt to Mr. John Vanderbilt..., 1830 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Receipt for tuition of son of Judge John Vanderbilt, 1830)
      A receipt to Mr. John Vanderbilt for the tuition and supplies for his son John in Erasmus Hall Academy, dated 1830 and signed by principal J. W. Kellogg. (This item was on display in the Museum Room of the EHHS Library for many years until 1973, which accounts for the serious fading.) John Vanderbilt Sr. was a prominent Flatbush resident and judge, d. 1877.
    - Receipts, School No. 1, 1871–1872 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      Receipts, School No. 1, Sept. 1871 to Sept. 30, 1872. (These are receipts signed by teachers for salary received.)
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Regents Exams
    - [Letters and instructions], 1875 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Regents of the University of the State of New York, 1875)
      • Instructions for administering the very first Regents examinations, dated Feb. 1, 1875. 6 pg.
      • Accompanied by an eight page letter to the Board of Regents, detailing the administration of the exams at Erasmus Hall Academy, the scores of each pupil, and adding some sharp criticism. Dated Flatbush, March 22, 1875, the letter is autographed by John M. Ferris, Abraham Lott, and John L. Zabriskie.
      • Also, covering letter from John M. Ferris to Dr. John L. Zabriskie, June 9, 1875.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Regents Grant
    - "Report of Committee on Application from Jacob Lefferts and others for an Incorporation by the Style of the Trustees of Erasmus Hall, King's County", 1787 August 24 (Offsite-box RC-10b, Frame Erasmus Hall Academy—Regents Grant)
      The one-page report recommends accepting the request that "John VanDerBilt and the eighteen other persons for that Purpose nominated in the said Instrument may be incorporated by the name and Style of The Trustees of Erasmus Hall in Kings County... ."
      The 9 x 13" document is signed by John Jay, first Chief Justice of the U.S.; Judge Egbert Benson, first president of the N. Y. Historical Society; and Rev. Mr. William Linn.
      Under glass in a 14 x 20" frame. Presented to Erasmus Hall High School by Judge Russell Benedict (1859–1936), who resided at 104 Buckingham Road, Flatbush. Judge Benedict was a Justice of the Supreme Court of N.Y. (2nd Judicial Dist.), 1911–1925. (See Who's Who in America, 1930s editions.)
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Register of Students
    - [Letter from Robert G. Strong regarding a list of the Academy's scholars since its founding], [1815–1846], 1889 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      Holograph letter, signed by Robert G. Strong, Principal of the Academy, with reference to compiling a list of all of the Academy's scholars since its founding. "I have succeeded in securing six hundred and thirty-eight names (638) between the years of 1815–1846." Letter dated Feb. 9, 1889.
    - [Register and list], 1873 May 1, undated (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • Register of 13 students aged 13–17, and their grades. n.d. 1 p. (Includes Charlotte E. Vanderveer, age 15; John A. Ditmas, age 14, etc.)
      • List of students enrolled as of May 1, 1873, and amount each paid. 4 p.
    - Circular and Catalogue of Erasmus Hall Academy, 1881, 1885, 1886 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Catalogues)
      The Circular and Catalogue of Erasmus Hall Academy for the years 1881, 1885, and 1886 list the names of the students then enrolled.
      (For full bibliographic citation, see Erasmus Hall Academy—Catalogue)
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Report Card
    - Report card of John Bollinger, 1875 February 19 (Offsite-box RC-2, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Report Card)
      Report card of John Bollinger, dated Feb. 19, 1875, Jared Hasbrouck, Principal. Marks were on a scale of 1 to 5.
      This report card has been heavily damaged by cellophane tape, but is still legible.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Restoration
    - Newspaper clippings regarding plans for destroying or moving Academy, and finally, plans to restore it, undated (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall History)
      See also Erasmus Hall High School—165th anniversary of founding (1952)
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Students
    - [Composition by Alexander C. Snyder], 1868 January 17 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder "Skating in Prospect Park")
      Composition written Jan. 17, 1868 by Alexander C. Snyder, a pupil in the Academy, who later became vice president of the Broadway Trust Co. The composition deals with skating in Prospect Park.
    - [Letter to Robert A. Finlay], undated (Offsite-box RC-7)
      A letter written to "Master Robert A. Finlay, Flatbush, L.I.," who was a student at Erasmus Hall. The letter concerns letters, clothing and a toothbrush sent to him at the Academy.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Students—Photographs
    - [Photograph of Principal Robert G. Strong with students], 1883 November 8 (Offsite-box RC-8a, Folder Faded sepia photograph...)
      Faded sepia photograph in 11 ½ x 13 ½" frame, showing Rev. Robert G. Strong, principal, with the students on the steps of the Academy. Dated Nov. 8, 1883. Received Jan. 24, 1966; donor unknown.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Teacher Salary
    - [Letter from John Williamson requesting a raise], 1867 October 5 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      Letter dated Oct. 5, 1867, from John Williamson, a teacher, asking for an increase in salary to $1,000. "I should at least receive as much as an ordinary clerk, & as much as will afford me a livelihood. The laborer is worthy of his hire."
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Transfer to City of Brooklyn for Use as Public High School, 1896
    - [Program, tickets, newspaper clippings], 1896 October 14 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Transfer of Erasmus Hall Academy...)
      • Original program and tickets of admission for the formal transfer ceremony, held Oct. 14, 1896 in the Flatbush Reformed Dutch Church.
      • Also, newspaper clippings.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Treasurer's Reports
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1871–1874 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • Treasurer's Report, Oct. 11, 1871. (with) Report of Committee to examine Treasurer's Report, Oct. 13, 1871.
      • Treasurer's Report, Nov. 16, 1872. (with) Report of Committee to examine Treasurer's Report, Nov. 9, 1872.
      • Treasurer's Report, Dec. 20, 1873.
      • Treasurer's Report, Oct. 2, 1874. (with) Report of Committee to examine Treasurer's account, Oct. 7, 1874.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Trustees
    - [Lists of trustees], 1900, undated (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Lists of Academy Trustees compiled by Willis Boughton)
      Typewritten lists of Trustees arranged by family (e.g., "Members of the Lefferts family who have served as Trustees.") Compiled by Willis Boughton in writing the Chronicles of Erasmus Hall. Includes 3 pg. letter written and signed by Cornelius L. Wells, minister of the Flatbush Reformed Dutch Church, Dec. 31, 1900.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Trustees' Meetings—Minutes
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1787–1839 (Offsite-box RC-18, Volume Minutes (1787–1839))
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1839–1880 (Offsite-box RC-18, Volume Minutes (1839–1880))
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1880–1896, 1904 (Offsite-box RC-18, Volume Minutes (1880–1896, 1904))
    - Minutes [drafts], 1871–1894 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • 1871 Oct. 14
      • 1872 Nov. 16
      • 1873 Dec. 23
      • 1874 Mar. 30, Apr. 20, June 13, July 14, Oct. 10
      • 1875 Feb. 13
      • 1878 July 27
      • 1886 March 6
      • 1892 all meetings
      • 1893 March 3, Aug. 12
      • 1894 Aug. 14
      These are rough drafts of the Trustees' meetings, mostly written by J. L. Zabriskie, who served as Trustee from 1855 until his death in 1895.
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Trustees' Meetings—Notice
    - [Original notice issued by Dr. John B. Zabriskie, Clerk of the Board], 1844 April 13 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Notice of Trustees' Meeting, 1844)
      An original notice issued by Dr. John B. Zabriskie, Clerk of the Board, to Jeremiah Lott, informing him that an extra meeting of the Trustees will be held Saturday, April 13, 1844, 7 P.M. (This item was on display in the museum room of the EHHS library for many years until 1973; this accounts for the serious fading.)
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Trustees' Report
    - [Letter and reply], 1866 December 17, undated (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • Letter from S. B. Woolworth, of Regents of the University of the State of New York, regarding failure of Academy to submit Annual Report.
      • Draft of reply by J. L. Zabriskie, secretary, dated Dec. 17, 1866.
    - [Reports], 1867–1870 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • Report of Trustees for year ending Sept. 30, 1867 (blank copy; not filled in)
      • Report of Trustees for year ending Sept. 30, 1868 (rough and finished drafts)
      • Report of Trustees for year ending Sept. 30, 1869
      • Report of Trustees for year ending Sept. 30, 1870
  - Erasmus Hall Academy—Views
    - Photographs of Erasmus Hall Academy, primarily original 19th century views, [1800s] (Offsite-box RC-9a, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Views)
    - [Engraved wood block], circa 1823 (Offsite-box RC-10a, Folder Original / wood engraved blocks of Erasmus Hall Academy)
      Earliest known view of Erasmus Hall Academy is a wood engraving executed c. 1823, appearing on an advertisement for the Academy, found in Records Case, Drawer 1 ("Erasmus Hall Academy—Advertisements"). Also reproduced at p. 251 of v. 1 of Stiles' History of Kings Co. History of Kings Co. (1884), with the incorrect date of 1850.
      The same view is reproduced in Cabinet of Instruction, Literature and Amusement (v. I, 1829, p. 432) (Records Case, Drawer 16), and in Williams' New-York Annual Register (1831, opp. p. 159) (Records Case, Drawer 16).
      The original engraved wood block from which this print was made is found in Records Case, Drawer 10.
    - Color reproduction from early 20th cent. calendar, [1826 October] (Offsite-box RC-9b, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—1826—color reproduction of original painting)
      Original watercolor by C. Burton dated Oct. 1826, 20 x 29", framed to 30 x 40"; formerly located in EHHS library, archives room; now in New-York Historical Society museum collection, accession number 1979.81.
    - [Engraved wood block], circa 1860 (Offsite-box RC-10a, Folder Original / wood engraved blocks of Erasmus Hall Academy)
      Wood engraving of the Academy appears as frontispiece in the Prospectus of Erasmus Hall Academy (1860) (in Records Case, Drawer 1, "Erasmus Hall Academy—Catalogues").
      Original wood engraved block from which this print was made is found in Records Case, Drawer 10.
    - [Photographs of boarders], 1880s–1890s (Offsite-box RC-9a, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—19th century group photos)
    - [Photograph of Principal Robert G. Strong with students], 1883 November 8 (Offsite-box RC-8a, Folder Faded sepia photograph...)
    - Original pencil drawings of the interior of the old Academy building, 1897 (Offsite-box RC-13)
      Probably made by students under the instruction of Allen B. Doggett. Four drawings. Also, one set of negative and positive glossy photostats of the four drawings.
    - Small dish made of Austrian china with full color view of Erasmus Hall, Flatbush, N.Y. [NOT PRESENT], circa 1900 (Box [unknown])
    - A group of photographs, prints, etc. of both the Academy and High School, undated (Offsite-box RC-9a, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy / High School—Views 8x10″ or smaller)
  - Erasmus Hall Athletic Field
    - Erasmus Hall Athletic Field, 1922 November 8 (Offsite-box RC-7)
      Original certificate of incorporation granted by Secretary of State of New York State to the Erasmus Hall Athletic Field Association, Inc.; dated Nov. 8, 1922.
  - Erasmus Hall High School—25th anniversary of transfer to City of Brooklyn (1921)
    - [Press release, program, photographs], [1921] (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall High School—Twenty-fifth Anniversary (1921))
      • Nine-page press release concerning celebration.
      • Program for the pageant entitled "The Tradition" which was given in October, 1921. (6 copies)
      • Photographs, most 8 x 10".
  - Erasmus Hall High School—125th anniversary of charter (1912)
    - [Invitation, souvenir program, newspaper clippings], 1912 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall High School—One Hundred Twenty-fifth Anniversary (1912))
      • Original invitation, souvenir program, and newspaper clippings printed in conjunction with the 125th anniversary celebration and pageant.
      • Brooklyn Life, v. 46, no. 1180 (Oct. 12, 1912), with photos of pageant.
    - [Panoramic photograph of pageant participants], 1912 (Offsite-box RC-8b, Folder 1912 Pageant photos)
      Large size photos (8 x 24") of 1912 pageant participants. One copy flat (cracked in half); one copy tightly rolled (brittle).
    - Mounted photographs, 1912 (Offsite-box RC-8a, Folder 1912 pageant 10 mounted photographs)
      Set of 10 9 ½ x 7 ½" photographs mounted on uniform mounts, taken by F. A. Walter, photographer, 510 Fulton Street, Bklyn. From Dr. McNeill, Jan. 18, 1956.
    - [Scrapbook of photographs], 1912 (Offsite-box RC-8b, Folder Scrapbook of the 1912 Pageant)
      Large leather scrapbook, about 14 ½ x 18 ½", with mounted 8 x 10 photographs.
    - [Scrapbook of letters], 1912 (Offsite-box RC-8b, Folder Scrapbook of the 125th Anniv. of EHHS, 1912)
      Scrapbook, approx. 12 x 14", containing letters from person invited to attend the 1912 pageant. There are autograph letters of a number of prominent people, including Charles Evans Hughes of the U. S. Supreme Court; John A. Dix, Governor of New York; William J. Gaynor, Mayor of New York City; Nicholas Murray Butler of Columbia University; etc. Also included are newspaper clippings, tickets, ribbons, etc.
    - Postcards issued for the event, 1912 (Offsite-box RC-9a, Folder Erasmus Hall High School—Postcard Views)
      • "The Erasmus Pageant... Set of Eleven Colored Post Cards.. ."
      • "Official Souvenirs... set of one dozen (black and white) Post Cards.. ."
  - Erasmus Hall High School—150th anniversary of charter (1937)
    - [Invitations, programs, articles, photographs], 1937 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall High School—One Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary (1937))
      Folder containing numerous items, including:
      • Invitations and ticket to pageant
      • Programs of Civic Night and Education Night Exercises (Oct. 7–8, 1937)
      • Numerous newspaper articles and photographs.
    - Material relating to the pageant held to mark the sesquicentennial of the school (box 1 of 2), 1937 (Offsite-box MS-24)
    - Material relating to the pageant held to mark the sesquicentennial of the school (box 2 of 2), 1937 (Offsite-box MS-25)
    - Photographs, 1937 (Offsite-box RC-8a, Folder Pageant—1937 photos (2 folders))
      • 4 x 5" size taken by student.
      • 4 ½ x 6 ½" size taken by W.P.A. (Project 6022).
      • 8 x 10" size, including official Board of Ed. photos
      • Album with red leatherette cover.
    - [Invitation engraving plates], [1937] (Offsite-box RC-8a, Folder 150th Anniversary Celebration (Engraving Plate) (Invitation and Program))
      Original Tiffany engraved plates used to print the invitations to the pageant. Housed in original box from Tiffany's.
  - Erasmus Hall High School—165th anniversary of charter (1952)
    - [Program, photograph, newspaper clippings], 1952 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall—165th Anniversary, 1787–1952)
      This celebration was held to re-dedicate the newly restored Erasmus Hall Academy building on the campus. The Regents held their December meeting in the Academy as their part of the celebration. Newspaper clippings, many photographs, and copies of the official program are on file.
    - Photographs of celebration taken by the New York Times, 1952 (Offsite-box RC-8a, Folder EHHS—165th Anniversary (1952))
      2 photos, 11 x 14".
    - Erasmus Hall High School—One Hundred Sixty-Fifth Anniversary, 1952 (Offsite-box MS-26)
  - Erasmus Hall High School—175th anniversary of charter (1962)
    - [Programs, article], 1962 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall High School—175th Anniversary, 1787–1962)
      • "175th Year Fete Held at Erasmus." In: Flatbush, May 1962 issue.